Pola Nirenska Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
- Books and Articles (Box [shelf])
  - Articles and Clippings (Box-folder 24/7-9, Box-folder 28/28)
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 28/28)
The tape consists of programming recorded from television. The last programs were probably recorded accidentally by continuously recording after the relevant programs.
13 "In memory of those I loved who are no more"
I. Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers [?]: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie
Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
II. Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Jeff Bliss, Debra Caplowe, Amy Dowling, Rima Faber, Susan Hannen, Jan
Tievsky costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
III. Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
IV. The train (1990)
music: "Suntreader," Carl Ruggles
dancers: Rima Faber (Mother), Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, Meryl
W. Shapiro
costume designer: Nirenska
The movements from the Holocaust tetralogy were recorded on different occasions. Life was filmed during the early 1980s; Dirge was recorded in 1988; the rehearsal of The train was filmed in Nirenska's studio in 1990.
14, 15 A celebration of dance, 1988 Feb. 5, John F. Kennedy Center for the Performing Arts [2 copies]
Out of sorts (premiere)
music: Claude Bolling
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting designer: David Covey
Web (1987)
music: Jon Hassell
dancer: Shawn Womack
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting designer: David Covey
Woman #1 (1987)
music: Anthony Davis
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting designer: David Covey
I found my grandfather dead (premiere)
music: Arnold Schoenberg
dancer: Tish Carter
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting designer: Tish Carter
Shout (1986)
music: Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
lighting designer: David Covey
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Jeff Bliss, Debra Caplowe, Amy Dowling, Rima Faber, Susan Hannen, Jan Tievsky
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
lighting designer: David Covey
The program was part of the Kennedy Center's "Washington, front and center!" series. Choreography by Lloyd Whitmore and Tish Carter was also featured as part of "A celebration of dance." The quality of the recording is poor.
16 Everything (A) / Bach 3 movements / Liz (SP)
Wounded (1982)
music: Concerto for piano and orchestra, "Allucinante," Alberto Ginastera
dancer: Betsy Eagan
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Three sculptures, "Amity," "The knot"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
"Amity" dancers: Betsy Eagan, Stephanie Simmons, Carrie Wilcox
"The knot" dancers: Letitia Carter, Susan Hannen, Jenifer Litwin
costume designer: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Nirenska
set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds
Commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
Longing
music: La plus que lente, Claude Debussy; performed by Peter Frankel
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Wounded (1982) (Nirenska's comments in background)
Three sculptures, "The eternal insomnia of the earth"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Colette Yglesias
costume designers: Stan Fowler, Sandy Asay, Nirenska
set designers: Stan Fowler, Alex Rounds
Commissioned by Washington Dance Repertory
Bag lady
music: Claude Bolling, Jean-Pierre Rampal
dancer: Rima Faber
Departures [?]
music: Bachiana brasileira no. 1, Heitor Villa-Lobos
dancer: Cathy Payne
Exits
"Rage, rage against dying of the light" (1968)
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray..."
"Do not go gently into that good night"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Liz Lerman
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
quotations: Dylan Thomas
Weed (Trip) (1983)
music: The Modern Jazz Quartet
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Laughter
music: Eugène Bozza
dancer: Liz Lerman
Tired magician
music: William Russel, Henry Dixon Cowell
dancers: Nirenska, Diane Floyd, Meryl W. Shapiro, Jan Tievsky
Encounters and goodbyes (1984, original concept 1965)
music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio
dancers: Rima Faber, mother; Susan Hannen, child; Jan Tievsky, bad influence
Diane Floyd, good influence; Greg Reynolds, young man
Jewish song (The old and the new) (1984)
music: traditional, performed by Richard Tucker
dancer: Liz Lerman
Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers [?]: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
The works were recorded in various settings; some are rehearsals on stage or in the studio and some are performances. Recordings of rehearsals are usually of better quality than recordings of performances. Only the beginning of Life is recorded.
17 Bach [extra copy]
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
The divided self, Glen Echo Dance Theater (world premiere with introduction)
music: Symphony no. 4, Roger Goeb; performed by the Japan Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra
dancers: Jan Tievsky, Cheryl Koehler
There is only a brief introduction to The divided self.
18 "In memory of those I loved who are no more" [copy of #13, Gertrude Shurr's address on box]
I. Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers [?]: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
II. Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Jeff Bliss, Debra Caplowe, Amy Dowling, Rima Faber, Susan Hannen, Jan Tievsky
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
III. Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
IV. The train (1990)
music: "Suntreader," Carl Ruggles
dancers: Rima Faber (Mother), Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, Meryl
W. Shapiro
costume designer: Nirenska
The movements from the Holocaust tetralogy were recorded on different occasions. Life was filmed during the early 1980s; Dirge was recorded in 1988; the rehearsal of The train was filmed in Nirenska's studio in 1990.
19 Dirge only
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Rima Faber, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Dirge is rehearsed twice. Nirenska can be heard commenting in the background on lighting and various other aspects of the performance.
20, 21, 22 Copy of dances [3 copies]
Tired magician
music: William Russel, Henry Dixon Cowell
dancers: Nirenska, Diane Floyd, Meryl W. Shapiro, Jan Tievsky
Encounters and goodbyes (1984, original concept 1965)
music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio
dancers: Rima Faber, mother; Susan Hannen, child; Jan Tievsky, bad influence; Diane Floyd, good influence; Greg Reynolds, young man
Jewish song (The old and the new) (1984)
music: traditional, performed by Richard Tucker
dancer: Liz Lerman
Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers [?]: Rima Faber, Carol Anderson, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Rima Faber, Betsy Eagan, Susan Hannen, Carrie Wilcox, Colette Yglesias
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Weed (Trip) (1983)
music: The Modern Jazz Quartet
dancer: Susan Hannen
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey, 1968)
music: J. S. Bach
The divided self, Glen Echo Dance Theater (world premiere with introduction)
music: Symphony no. 4, Roger Goeb; performed by the Japan Philharmonic Symphony Orchestra
dancers: Jan Tievsky, Cheryl Koehler
The works were recorded in various settings; some are rehearsals on stage or in the studio and some are performances. Recordings of rehearsals are usually of better quality than recordings of performances. Nirenska appears on stage during the applause after the performance of The divided self.
23 Dances "Bad"
Dancin' man
starring: Jeff Hyslop
featuring: Ann Reinking, Frank Augustyn, Karen Kain, Honi Coles
producer and director: Bernard Picard
choreographers: Ann Ditchburn, Kirsteen Etherington, Eva Von Gencsy, Jeff Hyslop
"Alive from off center"
Pages from the book of rain
performers: Maasai
choreography director: Gary Hurst
music: Global Rain Music
Parafango
director: Charles Atlas
choreographer: Karole Armitage
performers: Karole Armitage, Michael Clark, Philippe Decoufle, Jean Guizerix, Joseph Lennon, Nathalie Richard, David Linton; music: David Linton
Dancin' man
Recorded from Maryland Public Television, and "Alive from off center" is recorded from channel 32, Washington, DC. There is miscellaneous programming between and after the two dance programs.
24, 25, 26 Concert at dance place, July 28 and 29, 1990 [3 copies]
Welcome by Debra Riley, staff person at Dance Place
Introduction by Rima Faber
Stillpoint (premiere)
music: The unanswered question, Charles Ives
dancer: Rima Faber
costume designer: Nirenska
Introduction by Sharon Wyrrick
"In memory of those I loved who are no more"
I. Life (Whatever begins also ends) (1982)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, Meryl W. Shapiro, Carrie
Wilcox, Rima Faber
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
II. Dirge (1981)
music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch
dancers: Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, Meryl W. Shapiro, Carrie
Wilcox, Rima Faber
costume designer: Terri Hume Prell
III. Shout (1986)
music: Hatred of the filthy bomb, Lou Harrison
dancer: Sharon Wyrrick
costume designer: Beth Burkhardt
IV. The train (premiere)
music: "Suntreader," Carl Ruggles
dancers: Rima Faber (Mother), Paula Camilli, Heather Doerbecker, Jan Taylor, Meryl
W. Shapiro
costume designer: Nirenska
Production Staff:
stage manager: Timothea Howard
lighting designer: Betsy Toth
production manager: Rima Faber
technical director: Stefan Johnson
technical assistant: Brian McGahren
The concert is a celebration of the culmination of Nirenska's work and her eightieth birthday. The introductions by Rima Faber, consisting of biographical information, and Sharon Wyrrick, about the Holocaust tetralogy, are informative. The program was partially funded by the National Endowment for the Arts.
Films
Double concerto in d minor (dedicated to Doris Humphrey)
music: J. S. Bach
Recorded in 1965
Exits
"Rage, rage against dying of the light" (1968)
"Bless me now with your fierce tears, I pray..."
"Do not go gently into that good night"
music: Evelyn Lohoefer
dancer: Liz Lerman
costumes: Terri Prell
quotations: Dylan Thomas
From Phyllis S. Legters
Unidentified [2]
Audiotapes
[Title of dance work (music: Title of composition and/or composer) date [note]]
American folk suite, "Complaining old man," "Three old women," "Two young girls," (music: accompanied by Elizabeth Wilson Hughes, voice and dulcimer)
American folk suite, "If I had a ribbon," fourth movement, (music: accompanied by Elizabeth Wilson Hughes, voice and dulcimer) [choreographic notes]
American folk suite, "Old woman," sixth movement (music: accompanied by Elizabeth Wilson Hughes, voice and dulcimer) ["Chopped bad version"]; The four horsemen of the apocalypse (music: Anton Webern)
Avenue of escape, "Brandy," first movement (music: Béla Bartók)
Avenue of escape, "Brandy," first movement (music: Béla Bartók); "De los angele" and eight celli; Longing (music: La plus que lente, Claude Debussy)
Bag lady (music: Claude Bolling and Jean-Pierre Rampal); Laughter (music: Eugène Bozza)
Barbaric suite (music: Barbaric dance suite for piano, Priaulx Rainier) 1957 Nov. 19
The bee oracles for tenor or baritone solo, flute, oboe, violin, cello, and harpsichord, Priaulx Rainier, 1976 Sept. 2 [clipping enclosed]
"Bounces, slow legs"
"Capitol of the world," (George Antheil) 1956 March 16 [Ballet Theatre Orchestra -- Joseph Levine, Roy Fitzel dancing]; Trois pièces brèves, Jacques Ibert; Mikrokosmos, Béla Bartók [Serly]
"Collaboration," "Drama," Exits ("3 exit") (music: Evelyn Lohoefer, quotations: Dylan Thomas); Laughter (music: Eugène Bozza)
Cycle for declamation for solo soprano, tenor, or baritone; Sonata for viola and piano; Dance of the rain for tenor and guitar; Priaulx Rainier, 1976 April 1 [Discussion of Rainier's childhood in South Africa precedes the music, envelope enclosed] Departures (music: Heitor Villa-Lobos) [performance tape, choreographic notes]
Departures or Quartet for convergent figures (music: Heitor Villa-Lobos, Quartet choreography: Beth Osgood)
Dirge (music: Concerto grosso no. 1, Ernest Bloch); Encounters and goodbyes (music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio)
The divided self (music: Symphony no. 4, Roger Goeb)
Double concerto in d minor (music: J. S. Bach); Life is so daily (music: Lukas Foss) [rehearsal tape]
Double concerto in d minor (music: J. S. Bach); Three sculptures (music: Evelyn Lohoefer) 1981 May 1 [Glen Echo Dance Theater tape]
Duet with Beth Osgood, first version
"EAI," 1956 Dec. 10; Hal Layne, 1956 Dec. 30 [test record]; "Phillips practice," 1956 Nov.; American folk suite, "Yankee girl," (music: accompanied by Elizabeth Wilson Hughes, voice and dulcimer); "Hangman," 1957 Jan. 16
Encounters and goodbyes (music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio)
Encounters and goodbyes (music: Sonata no. 3 [?], Norman Dello Joio); "Union 4;" "Warfield;" complaint to Washington School of Ballet
Exits (music: Evelyn Lohoefer, quotations: Dylan Thomas)
Exits ("3 death dances") (music: Evelyn Lohoefer, quotations: Dylan Thomas) [choreographic notes]; Vigil by the sea, "Lament," second movement (music: Song attributed to William Byrd); Sonata for dancers [?] (music: Henry Purcell, choreography: Virginia Freeman)
The four horsemen of the apocalypse (music: Anton Webern) [2]
The four horsemen of the apocalypse, "Death," fifth movement (music: Anton Webern); Exits (music: Evelyn Lohoefer, quotations: Dylan Thomas)
The four horsemen of the apocalypse, "Death," fifth movement (music: Anton Webern) [performed by Beth Osgood]; Three sculptures, "Insomnia of the Earth," first movement (music: Evelyn Lohoefer) [2]
"Four on position"
Homage
Improvisations by Evelyn Lohoefer
"Jazz"
"Jour -- three study;" The eternal fool (music: Abbe Nieman); A scarecrow remembers (music: Adda Heynssen, Harburg, Gorney)
Lewis, Joe (Joseph), "exp. voice" [costume designer]
Lohoefer, Evelyn and Beth Osgood Chanock
Madeira School
Miscellaneous
Organ gloriana, Two primordial canticles, Requiem, Priaulx Rainier, 1976 Nov. 1
Piano sonatas nos. 1 and 3, Paul Hindemith
The queen (Two queens) (music: G. Orville Trondson)
Strange visit (music: Béla Bartók)
Studies in modern dance, "Jazz study [?]," "Birds," third movement (music: Evelyn Lohoefer)
"They never came back"
Three sculptures, "Eternal insomnia of the earth," first movement (music: Evelyn Lohoefer) [2]
Three sculptures, "The knot," third movement (music: Evelyn Lohoefer) 1962 July 4 [rehearsal tape]
Vivaldi, Antonio [choreographic notes]
Record Albums
As you remember them, Time Life demonstration record. [45]
Bach, J. S. Prelude in e-flat minor, I call upon thee, Jesus, Victor 6786. [cracked]
Bartók, Béla. Music for string instruments, percussion, and celesta, Capitol L-8048.
Bloch, Ernest. Concerto grossi nos. 1 and 2, Mercury SR 90223.
Britten, Benjamin. War requiem, London A-4255.
Campbell, P. "Ev'rybody loves Saturday night;" Sigman and P. Faith, "True or false," Columbia 40115.
Cole, Nat King. The Nat King Cole golden treasury "unforgettable," Capitol SY 5155-61
"Dilemma," "Shepherd," Audiodisc 3292.
Folk music from Poland, Folklore F 001 [45]
Garner, Erroll. Erroll Garner rhapsody, Atlantic ALP 11216.
Garner, Erroll. Erroll Garner of the piano, Savoy MG-15001.
Lavalle. Band of America march; Sousa, John Philip. Stars and stripes forever, RCA Victor 447-0086. [45]
Martin. "Waltzing bugle boy;" Maxwell. "Ebb tide," London 1358
Mercer, Johnny and Harold Arlen. "Blues in the night;" S. Weiss. "Who kissed me last night?" Columbia 39813.
Moussorgsky, Modest. Pictures at an exhibition, RCA Victor DM 1249. [cracked]
Piaf, Édith. Chansons parisiennes, Columbia FL 9501.
Rainier, Priaulx. Barbaric dance suite (Quartet for strings), Gramophone special recording. [2]
Sinatra, Frank. "Take a chance," "Young-at-heart," Capitol F2703. [45]
Waring, Fred, and His Pennsylvanians. "Dry bones," "Ole Moses put pharaoh in his place," Decca 9-23948. [45]